We had crossed the French border.
We knew the end of our journey was near, so we made it last.
We were only flying a few hours a night, then spent the rest of the time eating and resting in pine forests.
During the day, the woods were quiet: wild animals were hiding in their dens, away from the heat, while the sound of cicadas invited us to nap.
It had been a beautiful day. Banjoko and I had stopped by a river to drink, then dozed off in a large pine tree.
Human voices echoed in the distance, but they were too far away to worry us.
The heat enhanced the forest scents, the smell of thyme, wormwood and pine needles baked by the sun.
Then, I noticed another smell. Very faint at first, but unmistakable. Banjoko noticed it too. Smoke.
This instantly shook us out of our slumber.
Around us, I could hear the forest waking up in panic. Birds calling, crickets shrieking, foxes and wild boars stampeding across the woods.
And in the distance, the crackling, snapping, popping of burning branches.
Banjoko and I took off in a frenzy. But where to go?
A blanket of smoke covered everything, clouds of black fumes billowed into the sky.
I was flying in a dense fog of panic, helplessly flapping my wings, unsure about what to do.
“The river!” I heard Banjoko’s voice behind me. “Bird, can you find it?”
I looked for my friend, but I couldn’t see him.
“Follow me”, I shouted. And I plunged towards the ground.
Travelling at lower altitude was unbearable.
The heat was scorching, the acrid smell of charred wood filled the air. But there was no other way.
The flames raced along, twigs, branches and trunks turning into ash all around us. We could hear the pitiful cries of creatures trapped in their burrows.
And then, I saw it ahead of me. The river.
I raced towards it and crashed on the riverbed.
My heart was racing, my lungs were scorched, but I could finally breathe.
Above me, the sky was ablaze with colour. I watched in horror as the forest disintegrated before me.
And then I remembered my friend.
“Banjoko!” I cried.
But he didn’t answer me.
I was alone.